Guide to the Tamiment Library Newspapers PERIODICALS.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library Newspapers
1873-2014
1960-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
Henle, John
PERIODICALS.001
290 Linear Feet in 657 boxes
The collection contains some 523 titles to date (September 2018). They were published by international and local labor unions in the United States and Canada, radical political parties (Anarchist, Communist, Maoist, Socialist, Trotskyist), the New Left, and by organizations representing civil rights movements (African-Americans, prisoners, etc.), peace movements, protest against the war in Vietnam (including titles published by American soldiers), activity in support of national liberation movements, student and youth activism, the counterculture, feminism and gay liberation, and other activism. While most of the titles are from the U.S., and of these about one fourth are from New York State, there are also some foreign titles, most from Western Europe, primarily Great Britain, France, Italy and Spain. The holdings continue to grow through donations and subscriptions. While the majority of the titles lack catalog records in BobCat, NYU's electronic library catalog, retrospective cataloging is taking place. An unpublished guide available in the library shows holdings information for each title.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Newspapers in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. The accession number associated with these materials is 1950.028.
Some materials were donated by John Henle in 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.016.
Arrangement
Serials in this collection are arranged alphabetically by title.
Historical Note
The Tamiment Library's collection of newspapers from labor and activist organizations traces its origins to the library of the Rand School of Social Science, established in 1906. Located just off Union Square in New York City, the Rand School was a workers education institution supported by the Socialist Party of New York, the garment trades unions, the Workman's Circle, and the Jewish Forward Association. The Rand School taught courses in economics, economic history, U.S. history, literature, socialist theory, and labor-management relations. In the mid-1920s the Rand School established a Trade Union Institute to train people interested in careers in trade union organizing and administration. The school also sponsored a vast array of cultural programs: theatre groups, poetry readings, and a workers chorus.
The Rand School's library, which was renamed the Meyer London Memorial Library in 1926, after the Socialist Congressman from Manhattan's Lower East Side, always played an important role in the school. By the 1930s it had one of the finest collections New York City documenting the history of labor and the left. In addition to the book collections many of the unions and progressive organizations associated with the school placed copies of their newspapers, journals, newsletters, leaflets, broadsides, and ephemeral pamphlet literature with the Library. By the end of World War II the Library had a large and growing collection of both current and historical newspapers. However, by the early 1950s the school was in financial trouble and it closed in 1956. For the next seven years the Meyer London Library was maintained with a subsidy from the Tamiment Institute, the educational arm of Camp Tamiment, a socialist summer camp in Pennsylvania's Pocono mountains.
In 1963 the Library was given to New York University. Under NYU administration the Tamiment Library grew rapidly, and today it has nearly 75,000 monograph volumes, a serial collection with more than 8,500 titles, a printed ephemera collection of nearly a million items, and 15,000 linear feet of archives, including personal papers, labor union records, photographs, film, graphics, and oral histories. The newspapers are part of the Library's serial collection. The holdings continue to grow through current subscriptions and donations of historical material.
Sources:
Swanson, Dorothy, "The Tamiment Institute/Ben Josephson Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives at New York University," Library Quarterly, 59:2 (1989), 148-161.
Custodial History
Newspapers in this collection have been accumulated by the Tamiment Library through various donations and subscriptions.
Related Materials
Additional serials collections created by the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives include:
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Labor Movement Serials (WAG 345)
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Communist and Socialist Serials (TAM 747)
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Housing Serials (TAM 729)
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Environmentalism Serials (TAM 732)
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Native American Serials (TAM 733)
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Women's Rights Serials (TAM 751)
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of LGBTQ Rights Serials (TAM 752)
Scope and Content Note
As of September 2018, the collection contains some 523 titles published by international and local labor unions in the United States and Canada, radical political parties (Anarchist, Communist, Maoist, Socialist, Trotskyist), the New Left, and by organizations representing civil rights movements (African-Americans, prisoners, etc.), peace movements, protest against the war in Vietnam (including titles published by American soldiers), activity in support of national liberation movements, student and youth activism, the counterculture, feminism and gay liberation, and other activism. While most of the titles are from the U.S., and of these about one third are from New York State, there are also some foreign titles, most from Western Europe, primarily Great Britain, France, Italy and Spain. The holdings continue to grow through donations and subscriptions. While the majority of the titles lack catalog records in BobCat, NYU's electronic library catalog, retrospective cataloging is taking place. An unpublished guide available in the library shows holdings information for each title.
African Americans -- Civil rights -- Newspapers.; Anarchism -- Newspapers.; Anarchism -- United States -- Newspapers.; Civil rights -- United States -- Newspapers.; Labor unions -- United States -- Newspapers.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Newspapers; Labor movement -- United States -- Newspapers.; Prisoners -- Civil rights -- United States -- Newspapers.; Peace movements -- United States -- Newspapers.; New Left -- United States -- Newspapers.; National liberation movements -- Foreign public opinion, American -- Newspapers.; Socialism -- Newspapers.; Social movements -- United States -- Newspapers.; Radicalism -- United States -- Newspapers.; Newspapers.; Feminism -- United States -- Newspapers.; Communism -- United States -- Newspapers.; Counterculture -- United States -- Newspapers.; Communism -- Newspapers.; Indians of North America -- Civil rights -- Newspapers.; Labor -- New York (State) -- New York -- Newspapers.; Gay liberation movement -- United States -- Newspapers.; Hispanic Americans -- Civil rights -- Newspapers.; Soldiers -- United States -- Political activity -- Newspapers.; Student movements -- United States -- Newspapers.; Socialism -- United States -- Newspapers.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States -- Newspapers.; Youth movements -- United States -- Newspapers.; Underground newspapers -- United States; Rand School of Social Science
- 30 Day Notice Place of publication: Seattle, Wash. Publisher: The Union, 1983-1985 (Box 429)
- 560 Free Press / Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen and Helpers Place of publication: Union City, N.J. Publisher: Int'l Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen & Helpers, Local 560, 1987-1989 (Box 139)
- 1199 Save Our Union News Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Save Our Union Coalition, 1984 (Box 128A)
- About Face Place of publication: Los Angeles, Calif. Publisher: GIs & Vietnam Vets Against the War, 1969 (Box 161)
- About Face!: The U.S. Servicemen's Fund Newsletter Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: U.S. Servicemen's Fund, 1969-1972 (Box 161)
- Aboveground Place of publication: Colorado Springs, Colo. Publisher: Aboveground, 1969-1970 (Box 161)
- Action Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: United Federation of College Teachers, 1964-1972 (Box 2)
- Action (ACT) Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: United Federation of College Teachers, 1968 (Box 2)
- Activist: Newspaper of the ACT for Disarmament Coalition Place of publication: Toronto, Canada Publisher: ACTIVIST Collective, 1986 (Box 2)
- ADA World Place of publication: Washington, D.C. Publisher: Americans for Democratic Action, 1971-1982 (Box 1)
- Advance Place of publication: Birmingham, Ala. Publisher: Trade Union Action League, 1983-1985 (Box 5)
- AFGE Government Standard Place of publication: Washington, D.C. Publisher: American Federation of Government Employees, 1985-2002 (Box 25)
- AFL-CIO News Place of publication: Washington, D.C. Publisher: American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1956-1984 (Box 5)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Researchers must use microfilm (Film R-7040)
- After the Fall Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: After the Fall Collective, undated (Box 5)
- Akwesasne Notes Place of publication: Roseveltown, N.Y. Publisher: Jerry Gambill, 1969-1975 (Box 7)
- Alarm Place of publication: Chicago, Ill. Publisher: International Workingmen's Association, 1885-1888 (Box 513)
  Researchers must use microfilm (Film R-7950)
- Al-Awda Place of publication: New Brunswick, N.J. Publisher: New Jersey Solidarity-Activists for the Liberation of Palestine, 2005 (Box 6)
- Alderson Hospitality House Place of publication: U.S.A., 1983 (Box 341)
- All Hands Abandon Ship! Place of publication: Newport, R.I. Publisher: BuRevPers, 1971-1972 (Box 161)
- All Ready on the Left Place of publication: Vista, Calif. Publisher: All Ready on the Left, 1970-1971 (Box 161)
- Allegro Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Associated Musicians of Greater New York, 1955-2010 (Box 9-17A)
- Allied Industrial Worker Place of publication: Beverly Hills, Calif. Publisher: International Union, Allied Industrial Workers of America, 1985-1992 (Box 18)
- The Ally Place of publication: Berkeley, Calif., 1968-1974 (Box 161)
- Alternative Place of publication: U.S.A. Publisher: Naperville Central High School, 1970 (Box 281)
- Amalgamated Laundry Workers Bulletin Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Laundry Workers Joint Board of Greater New York, 1953-1961 (Box 1)
- Amazon Place of publication: Milwaukee, Wis. Publisher: Amazon Collective, 1975-1979 (Box 19)
- America @ Work Place of publication: Washington, D.C. Publisher: AFL-CIO Public Affairs Dept., 1996-2005 (Box 18A-18B)
- America for All Place of publication: Chicago, Ill. Publisher: Socialist Party of America, 1932 (Box 19)
  Researchers must use microfilm (Film R-7276)
- American Labor Citizen Place of publication: San Francisco, Calif. Publisher: American Federation of Labor, 1939 (Box 487)
- American Mass Line Place of publication: Cleveland, Ohio Publisher: American Communist Workers Movement (Marxist-Leninist), 1970 (Box 237)
  Researchers must use microfilm (Film R-7897)
- American Student Place of publication: Cleveland, Ohio Publisher: American Student Movement (Anti-Imperialist), 1970 (Box 238)
- American Teacher Place of publication: Washington, D.C. Publisher: American Federation of Teachers, 1971-1993 (Box 25)
- The American Teacher Place of publication: Chicago, Ill. Publisher: American Federation of Teachers, 1983-1986 (Box 25)
- Analysis Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Analysis Associates, 1944-1957 (Box 29)
- The Anarchist Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Robert Steed, 1966 (Box 27)
- Anarchy Place of publication: San Francisco, Calif., 1985-1992 (Box 27)
- Anchorage Troop Place of publication: Anchorage, Alaska Publisher: Anchorage Troop, 1968-1972 (Box 161)
- APWU NewService Place of publication: Washington, D.C. Publisher: American Postal Workers Union, 2002-2002 (Box 300)
- The Arctic Arsenal Place of publication: Delta Junction, Alaska, 1971 (Box 161)
- The Ark Place of publication: Houston, Tex., undated (Box 31)
- Art & Artists Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Foundation for the Community of Artists, 1983 (Box 31)
- As You Were Place of publication: Fort Ord, Monterey, Calif. Publisher: G.I.'s at Fort Ord Military Complex, 1969-1970 (Box 161)
- Asianweek Place of publication: San Francisco, Calif. Publisher: Asian Week Pub. Co., 1992-1993 (Box 31A)
- Attitude Check Place of publication: Vista, Calif. Publisher: Movement for a Democratic Military, 1969-1970 (Box 161)
- Australasian Spartacist Place of publication: Sydney, Australia Publisher: Spartacist Publications, 1975-1977 (Box 399)
- Avante! Place of publication: Lisboa, Portugal Publisher: Partido Comunista Português, 1999 (Box 31)
- BAD Place of publication: Boston, Mass. Publisher: Y.M.I. INC., 1972-1973 (Box 23)
- Barb Wire Society Place of publication: Philadelphia, Pa., 1970 (Box 341)
- Barrage Place of publication: Fort Bill Publisher: Department of Defense Directive, 1972 (Box 161)
- Bay Area Painters News Place of publication: Oakland, Calif. Publisher: Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators and Paperhangers of America, Local Union No. 127, 1965-1973 (Box 32-33)
- BCTGM News Place of publication: Kensington, Md. Publisher: Bakery, Confectionery, Tobacco and Grain Millers Union, 1999-2000 (Box 36)
- Beacon Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Esso Tanker-Men's Association, 1941 (Box 37)
- The Bell Wringer Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Members for a Democratic Union, 1986-1992 (Box 37)
- Berkeley Barb Place of publication: Berkeley, Calif. Publisher: Scherr, Max, 1965-1979 (Box 37)
- Big Mama Rag Place of publication: Denver, Colo., 1974-1979 (Box 33)
- The Big Us Place of publication: Cleveland, Ohio Place of publication: Cleveland Movement, 1968 (Box 34)
- The Black Dwarf Place of publication: London, England, 1968-1970 (Box 39)
- Black Liberation Month News Place of publication: Chicago, Ill.. Publisher: Organizing Committee for a New African Liberation Support Committee, 1978-1985 (Box 46)
- Black Panther Place of publication: Oakland, Calif. Publisher: Black Panther Party, Ministry of Information, 1967-1976 (Box 38)
- The Black Voice, 1972 (Box 38)
- BME Marine Engineer Place of publication: Brooklyn, N.Y. Publisher: Brotherhood of Marine Engineers, AFL-CIO, 1956-1959 (Box 40)
- Boilermaker Reporter Place of publication: Kansas City, Kan. Publisher: Boilermakers' Publications, 1990-2010 (Box 44-44A)
- The Bond Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Committee for GI Rights, 1969-1974 (Box 161)
- Bragg Briefs Place of publication: Spring Lake, N.C. Publisher: GI's United Against the War in Vietnam, 1969-1975 (Box 161)
- British Workman Place of publication: London, England Publisher: S. W. Partridge, 1872 (Box 205)
- Brooklyn Bridge Place of publication: Brooklyn, N.Y., 1972-1973 (Box 46)
- Brooklyn Heights Press Place of publication: Brooklyn, N.Y. Publisher: Brooklyn Heights Press, 1957 (Box 46)
- The Brooklyn Longshoreman Place of publication: Brooklyn, N.Y. Publisher: International Longshoremen's Association, AFL-CIO, Local 1814, 1964 (Box 46)
- Brother: Male Liberation Newspaper Place of publication: Berkeley, Calif. Publisher: The Brother Collective, 1971-1975 (Box 46)
- Build the Nationwide Unemployed League Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: United Front Committee to Build the Nationwide Unemployed League, 1975 (Box 46)
- Bulletin Place of publication: Washington, D.C. Publisher: National Treasury Employees Union, 1977-1980 (Box 67)
- Bulletin of the New York Teachers Guild Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: New York Teachers Guild, 1935-1960 (Box 65-66)
- Cafeteria Call Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Cafeteria Employees Union, Local 302, HREBIU, AFL-CIO, 1950 (Box 74)
- Cahiers de Mai, 1968 (Box 43)
- California Prisoner Place of publication: Sacramento, Calif. Publisher: Prisoners Rights Union, 1983-1998 (Box 77)
- California Socialist Place of publication: Calif., 1981-1982 (Box 74)
- The Call Place of publication: Bell Gardens, Calif. Publisher The October League (M-L); Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist) (United States), 1972-1980 (Box 74, Box 75, Box 76)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  The following issues were donated by John Henle in January of 2016 and incorporated into the run of this publication: Volume 4, Number 3; Volume 5, Numbers 6, 11, 14, 19-21. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.016.
- Camden Tenant Place of publication: London, England Publisher: Camden Federation of Tenants and Residents Associations, 1972-1975 (Box 77)
- Camp News Place of publication: Chicago, Ill. Publisher: Chicago Area Military Project, 1970-1973 (Box 162)
- Canadian Transport Place of publication: Ottawa, Canada Publisher: Canadian Brotherhood of Railway, Transport, and General Workers, 1994 (Box 78)
- Catholic Agitator Place of publication: Los Angeles, Calif. Publisher: Los Angeles Catholic Worker, 1980-2001 (Box 84)
- The Catholic Worker Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: D. Day, 1935-2010 (Box 084A)
- Catonsville Roadrunner Publisher: Manchester 21, 1972 (Box 84)
- CCNY Messenger Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: City College of New York, 1998 (Box 111)
- Challenge / Young People's Socialist League Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Young People's Socialist League, 1956-1958 (Box 94)
- Challenge: Official Organ of the Young People's Socialist League Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: YPSL, 1958-1959 (Box 94)
- Challenge: The Revolutionary Newspaper Place of publication: Brooklyn, N.Y. Publisher: Progressive Labor Party, 1968-1987 (Box 88-93)
- Chartist Place of publication: London, England, 1972-1975 (Box 94)
- Chicago Bridge Place of publication: Chicago, Ill. Publisher: Chicago Flower Journal and Fire Enterprises, Inc., 1967 (Box 97)
- Chile Newsletter Place of publication: Berkeley, Calif. Publisher: Non-Intervention in Chile, 1976 (Box 97)
- CIR News / The Committee of Interns and Residents Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Committee of Interns and Residents, 1983-2010 (Box 85)
- Circle Check Buyer and Labor News Place of publication: Richmond, Va. Publisher: Trades Union Circle Check Association, 1897 (Box 97)
- Citizen Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: National Wallace for President Committee, 1948 (Box 99)
- Clarion Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Professional Staff Congress CUNY, 1972-2010 (Box 105-106A)
- The Clarion Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Clarion Publishing Association, 1932-1934 (Box 27)
- Class War for the Dictatorship of the Proletariat Place of publication: New York, N.Y., 1973 (Box 238)
- Clinton News Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Board of Publications of the General Organization of the De Witt Clinton Public High School, 1934-1935 (Box 74)
- CNT: portavoz de la CNT de España en el exilio Place of publication: Toulouse, France Publisher: C.N.T., 1957-1982 (Box 27)
- Coalition Place of publication: Scato, Calif. Publisher: The Coalition, 1972 (Box 162)
- Cogito Place of publication: Syracuse, N.Y., 1968 (Box 281)
- Collage Place of publication: New York, N.Y., undated (Box 107)
- Colorado Labor Advocate Place of publication: Denver, Colo. Publisher: AFL-CIO, 1987-2011 (Box 108-110A)
- Columbia Spectator Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Columbia University, 1968 (Box 108)
- Columbus Free Press Place of publication: Columbus, Ohio, undated (Box 107)
- Le Combat Syndicaliste Place of publication: Paris, France Publisher: Confederation Nationale du Travail, 1967-1982 (Box 27)
- Commonwealth Place of publication: Regina, Canada Publisher: New Democratic Party, 1977-1989 (Box 111-113)
- Commonwork Pamphlets Place of publication: New Haven, Conn., undated (Box 114)
- Communications Workers of America - District 1 Hot Line Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Communications Workers of America, 1983-1997 (Box 114)
- Communist, 1971 (Box 238)
- Communist Place of publication: U.S.A. Publisher: Central Committee of the Marxist-Leninist Party, 1970-1971 (Box 238)
- Convention Report Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: National Caucus of SDS Labor Committees, 1969 (Box 114)
- Convoy Place of publication: Cleveland, Ohio Publisher: Teamsters for a Democratic Union, 1976-1979 (Box 501)
- Cooperator Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: United Housing Foundation, 1967 (Box 108)
- Crazy Horse Spirit Place of publication: Rapid City, S.D. Publisher: Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 115A)
- CSA News Place of publication: Brooklyn, N.Y. Publisher: Council of Supervisors and Administrators, Local 1, American Federation of School Administrations, AFL-CIO, 2005-2010 (Box 116A)
- CSTG Press Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Civil Service Technical Guild Local 375, 1979-1980 (Box 115)
- Cuba internacional Place of publication: Havana, Cuba Publisher: Agencia Prensa Latina, 1974-1977 (Box 115A-115B)
- CWA News Place of publication: Washington, D.C. Publisher: Communications Workers of America, 1953-2010 (Box 71-73)
- Daily Compass Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: T.O. Thackery, 1952 (Box 117)
  Researchers must use microfilm (Film R-7026)
- Daily World Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Long View Pub. Co., 1968 (Box 116)
- Defenestrator Place of publication: Philadelphia, Pa., 2001-2002 (Box 115)
- Destroyer Place of publication: Philadelphia, Pa. Publisher: Philadelphia Resistance, 1970 (Box 162)
- Different Drummer Place of publication: Little Rock, Ark., 1970 (Box 117)
- Dispatcher Place of publication: San Francisco, Calif. Publisher: International Longshore and Warehousemen's Union, 1969-2010 (Box 118-120)
- Distributive Worker Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Distributive Workers of America, 1969-1990 (Box 121)
- District 2 Marine Engineer Place of publication: Brooklyn, N.Y. Publisher: District 2, Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association, AFL-CIO, 1961-1970 (Box 122)
- District Council 9 News / Painters District Council 9 of New York City Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Painters District Council 9, 1957-1966 (Box 316)
- Drunken Boat Place of publication: Brooklyn, N.Y. Publisher: Drunken Boat, 1993-1993 (Box 120)
- Dynamic! Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Young Communist League of the U.S.A., 1984-2001 (Box 123)
- Educational Notes Publisher: International Socialists, 1976-1976 (Box 123)
- Electrical Union World: Official Organ of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, Local 3 Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, 1965-2010 (Box 124-127A)
- Empire State Teacher Place of publication: Syracuse, N.Y. Publisher: Empire State Federation of Teachers, AFT, 1957-1965 (Box 127A)
- Enlisted Times Place of publication: San Francisco, Calif. Publisher: Military Studies Center, 1977 (Box 128)
- Equal Times Place of publication: Boston, Mass. Publisher: Eunice West, 1977-1979 (Box 128A)
- Equity News Place of publication: New York, N.Y. Publisher: Actor's Equity Association, 1982-2013 (Box 129-129A)